## ANDREW LEACH





## Economist. Data Scientist. Policy Analyst. Academic leader. Author.

I am an energy and environmental economist and Professor of Economics and Law at the University of Alberta. My research spans climate, energy and environmental economics and policy with a focus on climate change policies and the law. I have advised federal and provincial governments and provided policy analysis to public- and private-sector clients. I am also an avid data scientist, exploring ways to summarize and visualize energy and economic indicators. I am a prolific writer, with over 200 bylines in major Canadian outlets.

## **EXPERIENCE**

2006 - present University of Alberta, Faculty Member

Professor, Faculty of Arts (Economics) and Faculty of Law, 2022-present

**Professor, Alberta School of Business**, 2022

Associate Professor, Alberta School of Business, 2011-2022

**Enbridge Professor of Energy Policy, Alberta School of Business**, 2012-2015

Assistant Professor, Alberta School of Business, 2006-2011

2006 - present **Economics and Policy Consultant** 

Environmental policy development and evaluation. Policy advisor to federal and provincial

governments. Expert witness on energy, economic, and regulatory files.

2015 Government of Alberta, Chair, Climate Leadership Panel

2012 - 2013 Environment and Climate Change Canada, Visiting Scholar

2003 – 2006 **HEC Montréal, Faculty Member** 

Assistant Professor/Professeur Adjoint, Institute of Applied Economics

**EDUCATION** 

2019 – 2020 LLM (Constitutional Law) University of Alberta

Thesis examined the constitutional anchors for climate change policies under the POGG, Trade

and Commerce, and Criminal Law powers of the federal government.

1999 – 2003 Ph.D. (Economics) Queen's University

Thesis applied numerical methods to examine the economics of climate change policy, including

distributional issues and the impacts of uncertainty and learning on optimal policy.

1998 – 1999 MA (Economics) University of Guelph

Focus on environmental, resource, and labour economics.

1994 – 1998 B.Sc. (Environmental Science) University of Guelph

Major: Environmental Economics and Policy.

**WORK PRODUCT** 

Publications Academic Publications aleach.ca/publications

Data Data and visualization project archive aleach.ca/projects

Visualization

Opinion Opinion Archive aleach.ca/opinion

LANGUAGES HOBBIES NON PROFIT

**English** - native I am an avid cyclist, occasional runner, **French** - proficient downhill and cross-country skier, hockey

downhill and cross-country skier, hockey player, and hobbyist woodworker. Edmonton Juventus Cycling Club. Past Board Member, River Valley Alliance and

yer, and nobbyist woodworker.

Board Member, River Valley Alliance at Economic Society of Northern Alberta.

Board of Directors, REACH Edmonton and